Guide to the Earl E. Fisk Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Earl E. Fisk papers
1911-1953
GEN MSS 342
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes) + 1 portfolio
Earl E. Fisk, British-born book collector, anthologist, writer, and insurance agent. Collection includes correspondence, writings, and other materials. Correspondence contains letters to and from writers, publishers and others, including Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., Warren Beck, John Chipman Farrar, Farrar, Straus and Company, Harry Hansen, Robert Cortes Holliday, H. L. Mencken, A. Edward Newton, Carl Van Vechten, and Eudora Welty. Many of the letters concern Haldane Macfall. Writings include typescripts of articles by Fisk and others, and page proofs for Fisk's "Lovely Laughter: An Anthology of Seventeenth Century Love Lyrics". Other materials include specimen pages,illustrations, greeting cards and bookplates by Fisk, Claud Lovat Fraser, and others, and a detailed typescript list of Fisk's book collection.
Fisk, Earl E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the Matthiessen Fund, 1956.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in the portfolio may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Earl E. Fisk, born in Britain in 1892, was an insurance agent, book collector, and casual literary agent to writers who were also his friends. After working as a professor of English at the University of Wisconsin, Fisk entered the insurance business, and became chairman of the National Association of Insurance Agents. At the same time, he continued collecting first editions of books by contemporary authors, including Max Beerbohm, A. E. Coppard, Claud Lovat Fraser, Holbrook Jackson, and A. Edward Newton. Although Fisk lived in Wisconsin for most of his adult life, he maintained a connection to the British literary scene. He actively promoted the work of authors whom he enjoyed, and he helped to place books by Haldane Macfall and Holbrook Jackson with American publishers. He also wrote many articles for The Bookman, and edited several books, including two collections of Elizabethan poetry and an edition of William Cobbett's Advice to Young Men and to Young Women.
Scope and Contents
The Earl E. Fisk Papers contain letters, writings, printed material and other papers by and related to Earl E. Fisk. The papers have been arranged into three series. Series I, Correspondence, consists primarily of letters from individuals, publishing companies and others to Fisk, as well as some of Fisk's replies. Many letters contain illustrated cards and bookplates. Series II, Writings, contains proofs and typescripts of articles and other writings by Fisk and others. Series III, Other Papers, contains Fisk's research files, consisting of lists, notes and newspaper clippings about book collecting and his own publications; printed materials, containing specimen pages, printed illustrations, and articles by various individuals; and other materials, consisting of a typescript list of Fisk's book collection, and lists of people to whom he sent Christmas cards. Restricted Fragile Papers contains materials from Series III.
Bookplates; Lovely laughter: an anthology of seventeenth century love lyrics; Beck, Warren, 1896-1986; Farrar, John Chipman, 1896-1974; Fisk, Earl E.; Fraser, Claud Lovat, 1890-1921; Hansen, Harry, 1884-1977; Holliday, Robert Cortes, 1880-1947; Macfall, Haldane, 1860-1928; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Newton, A. Edward (Alfred Edward), 1864-1940; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Welty, Eudora, 1909-2001; Alfred A. Knopf, Inc; Farrar, Straus, and Company
- Correspondence, 1911-1953; Series I; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  - Abramson, Ben. 1 TLS and 1 form- letter (with 3 paragraphs typed), Chicago, Ill., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Letter of Sept. 8 concerning Ben Hecht
  - Adams, James Donald. 1 TLS, New York, N. Y., 1947 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    With carbon copy of Fisk's reply, and clipping of an article by Adams
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., New York, 1926-52 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    Concerning Haldane Macfall, A. E. Coppard, Fisk's Lovely Laughter, and a reprint of a book by William Cobbett, edited by Fisk
    Includes: carbon typescripts of several replies by Fisk
    Includes: Letters from Alfred A. Knopf
    Includes: Letter from Blanche W. Knopf
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. Third-party correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes: carbon of TLS from [Knopf?] to Wilmarth S. Lewis
    Includes: copy of TL from Adolf Kroch to Alfred A. Knopf
    Includes: carbon copy of a TLS from Alfred A. Knopf to A. E. Coppard
  - Babb, James T. TLS, New Haven, 1950 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baer, Carlyle Solomon. ALS, Washington, D.C., 1925 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    With printed circular from the American Society of Bookplate Collectors and Designers
  - Beck, Warren. 3 ALS, 6 APCS, 1 TLS and 4 TPCS, Appleton, Wis., 1945-51 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    With a TLS from Carmen Beck to Fisk, 24 Oct. 1945
  - Benington, Wilson. ALS, London, 1931 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    With printed Christmas greeting from Eric Partridge Ltd.
  - Benthall, Dwinelle. 1 TLS and 1 TL, Hollywood, Cal., 1929, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Book-of-the-Month Club. 8 TLS, New York, N. Y., 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Accompanied by carbon typescript of a letter from Fisk to Schermann, 1950 Oct 22; and list of the British and American authors to whom Fisk sent letters requesting opinions on the work of A. E. Coppard
    Includes: Letters from Henry Scherman
  - Boyce, [Clara?]. ALS, Portsmouth, England, 1931 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Butcher, Fanny. TLS, Chicago, 1944 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cameron, Mrs. Alan C. Carbon of TLS from Fisk, 1950 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Collamore, H. B. TLS, Hartford, Conn., 1948 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cresset Press. TLS, London, 1930 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cunningham, Scott. 12 TLS and 2 ALS, Chicago, Ill., 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    With a TL (copy) from Fisk to Cunningham, enclosing a TL (copy) from T. R. Smith to Fisk, with original envelope, concerning Mr. Cunningham, and a copy of Fisk's reply
  - Danielson, Henry. 2 TLS, London, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Drinkwater, John and Daisy. Printed notice of change of address (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - E. Mathews (firm). 4 TLS, 1 ALS, and 1 Christmas greeting, 1931-49, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    With a carbon of a TLS from Fisk, 1951
    Includes: letters from Percy H. Muir
  - Faber and Faber. 5 TLS, London, 1946-49 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    With copy of a reply from Fisk
  - Farrar, John Chipman. 10 TLS, New York, N. Y., 1921-26 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Many letters concern The Bookman. With an engraved invitation to Farrar's wedding
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Farrar, Straus and Co., Box 1, folders 26-28
  - Farrar, Straus and Company. 32 TLS and 3 telegrams, New York, 1946-50 (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
    Accompanied 5 carbon typescripts of replies by Fisk
    Includes: Letters from John Chipman Farrar
    Includes: Letters from Roger W. Straus
  - Fleming, Mary. 1 TLS, New Brunswick, N. J., 1922 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gallatin, A. E. (Albert Eugene). ALS and 4 TLS, New York and Bar Harbor, Maine, 1944-46 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    Accompanied by 2 typescripts (one corrected) of Fisk's review of Gallatin's Sir Max Beerbohm: Bibliographical Notes, Cambridge, Harvard, 1944; two clippings concerning Max Beerbohm, and manuscript notes in Fisk's hand
  - George, Daniel. 1 TLS, Mill Hill, England, 1949 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - George H. Doran Company. Carbon of TLS from Fisk, 1926 Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Gunther, John. 2 TLS, Chicago, Ill., and New York, N. Y., 1923, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hadfield, John and Anna. Printed Christmas card, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    With engraving by Reynolds Stone
  - Hansen, Harry. 16 TLS, Chicago, Ill., and New York, N. Y., 1922-46 (Box 1, Folder 36-38)
    With the proof-sheets (2 leaves) for one of his articles
  - Henson, Mrs. 1 ALS, Mullingar, Ireland, [1929?] Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hergesheimer, Joseph. 3 TLS and 1 ALS, West Chester, Pa. and Stone Harbor, N. J., 1924-52 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    With 5 unsigned Christmas cards
  - Hill, Walter M. 1 TLS, Chicago, 1923 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Holliday, Robert Cortes. 9 ALS and 3 TLS, New York, N. Y., Englewood Cliffs and Sussex Co., N. J., 1920-47 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
    With 2 unsigned Christmas cards. With a TLS from Christopher Kilmer, 6 Jan. 1947, announcing Mr. Holliday's death
  - Holman, Robert. 2 TLS, Mahanoy City, Pa. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hynes, Frank J. 1 ALS, Springfield, Mass., 1935 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Concerning Haldane Macfall. With carbon copy of TLS from Fisk
  - James F. Drake, Inc. 2 TLS, New York, N. Y., 1924, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Letter of 1944 concerns Alfred Edward Newton
  - Janvier, Meredith. 2 TLS and one Christmas card, Baltimore, 1923-28 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Jonathan Cape Limited. 3 TLS, London, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Kennerley, Mitchell. Carbon of TLS from Fisk, 1911 Dec 12 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Kroch's International Bookstore. Form letter concerning Fisk's Persuasions to Joy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Lemperly, Paul. 3 ALS, Lakewood, Ohio, 1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    With 5 of Mr. Lemperly's bookplates
  - Little, Brown and Company. 1 TLS, Boston, Mass., 1927 Jul 12 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Littman, Frederic. 2 ALS, London, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Macfall, Haldane. 1 ALS, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Maclaren, Hamish, 1 TLS, Turville, Henley, England, [n.y.] Oct 29 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Markey, Gene. 2 ALS, Evanston, Ill., 1922-23 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    With an original caricature (signed) drawn for Fisk's Christmas Card, 1923, based on Joseph Hergesheimer's The Presbyterian Child [?], and a clipping about Markey
  - Matthews, Brander. 1 ALS and 1 ANS, New York, N. Y. and Greenwich, Conn., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Maule, Harry Edward. TLS, Garden City, N. Y., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Mencken, H. L. 11 TLS and 1 ANS, New York, N. Y. and Baltimore, Md. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    With a TPC from Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., regarding Mencken's Prejudices: Second Series
  - Morris, Frank M. 2 TLS, Chicago, Ill., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Newton, A. Edward. 11 TLS, Philadelphia, Pa., 1920-31 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    With Fisk's list, dated Sept. 1944, of ephemera printed by Newton
  - Philip C. Duschnes (firm). 1 TLS, New York, 1948 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Preston, Keith. 2 ALS and 1 TLS, Chicago, Ill., 1926-27 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Quiz (Powys Evans). 1 APCS to Capt. R. A. Walker [Georges Derry?], Kensington, [1922?] (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Redman, Ben Ray. 2 ALS, 2 TLS and 1 APCS, New York, N. Y., 1930-47 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    With a carbon of a TLS from Fisk
  - Rodgers, Elizabeth (Mrs. Robert A.). 1 ALS, Wilmette, Illinois, 1953 Oct 21 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Rota, Bertram. 3 TLS, London, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Sarett, Lew R. TLS, Evanston, Ill., 1925 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Schwartz, Jacob. 3 ALS, London, 1930-31 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    With a printed pamphlet concerning Edgar Allan Poe
  - Shepard, Morgan. 1 TLS, New York, 1911 Dec 12 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Shields, James. 1 TLS, Philadelphia, 1922 Sep 25 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Simon and Schuster, Inc. 8 TLS, New York, N. Y., 1927-31 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    With 2 carbon copies of TLS from Fisk
  - The Spectator. 1 form letter, London, [1922] (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Starrett, Vincent. 7 ALS, 4 TLS and 2 APCS, Chicago, Ill., 1924-49 (Box 2, Folder 74-75)
    Partially concerning Haldane Macfall
  - Stone, Wilbur Macey. 2 ALS and 1 TLS, East Orange, N. J., 1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster. ALS, New Haven, Conn., 1923 Jan 17 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Van Vechten, Carl. 4 TLS and 1 signed greeting card, New York, N. Y., 1926-51 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Viking Press. 2 TLS, New York, N. Y., 1944, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Wace & Co. Ltd., Process Engravers. 1 invoice to Alfred Knopf Ltd., 1931 Sep 29 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - The Walden Book Shops. 1 TL, Chicago, 1929 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Walter V. McKee, firm, publishers. 6 TLS to Earl E. Fisk, New York, 1928-30 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Accompanied by carbon typescript of TL from Fisk to McKee, and a TLS from McKee to Haldane Macfall, Aug. 3, 1928
  - Welty, Eudora. TLS, Jackson, Miss., 1950 Dec 2 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    Concerning A. E. Coppard
  - West, Herbert Faulkner. 2 ALS and a signed greeting card Hanover, N. H., 1949-50 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    With an enclosed photograph of Mr. West and Robert Frost
  - Whitaker, Michael J. G. 1 ALS, St. Johnsbury, Vermont, [1949] (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Wilson, Edmund. 2 APCS, New York, N. Y. and Wellfleet, Mass., 1951 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Wilson, Francis. ALS, [n.p.], 1921 Oct 3 (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Writings, 1921-1931; Series II; 0.2; (.5 box)
  - EARL E. FISK
    - "The Chesterton-Drinkwater-Lewis Affair". 2 corrected typescripts, one corrected, of an article for The Bookman, [1921] (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Lovely Laughter: An Anthology of Seventeenth Century Love Lyrics. Page proofs, [1931] (Box 3, Folder 89-90)
      Published: New York, Knopf, 1931
    - Typescript drafts of promotional notes [by Fisk?] about Lovely Laughter and Advice to Young Men (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - Holograph poem entitled "Epilogue to Lord Dunsany's 'The Flight of the Queen'" signed "HNR", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Typescript poem by unidentified entitled "To a Girl in a Black Leather Hat", 1924 Nov 2 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Strong, L. A. G. (Leonard Alfred George). Partial typescript of review(?) about "Mrs. Whitaker", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
- Other Papers, 1921-1953; Series III; 0.2; (.5 box)
  - RESEARCH FILES
    - Typescript list entitled "A Collection of Original Drawings and Books Illustrated by Lovat Fraser for sale by Alexander Greene" (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1922-50 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - PRINTED MATERIALS
    - Fisk, Earl E. Specimen pages from Advice to Young Men, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Fisk, Earl E. Page from Persuasions to Joy, with poem by George Herbert, [1927] (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Gillray, James. Color prints used in Fisk's edition of Advice to Young Men, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Lawrence, D. H. Specimen page from Birds, Beasts and Flowers, The Cresset Press Limited, London, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Shepard, Ernest H. Printed holiday greetings with illustrations, 1924, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Printed pages of poems with illustrations, by unidentified, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
      Back of pages say "Designed by A. Wyndham Payne, produced in England by The Chelsea Publishing Co., Printers Morland Press"
    - "Vera Willoughby: An Appreciation by James Laver", [1929] (Box 3, Folder 104)
      Included in: Current Literature and the Publishers' Miscellany, [London] no. 251, November, 1929, p. 370
    - Review of This Book Collecting Game, by A. Edward Newton, [1930] (Box 3, Folder 105)
      Included in: Current Literature and the Publishers' Miscellany, [London] no. 263, November, 1930, p. 437
    - Greeting cards and bookplates, 1950-53, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 106-108)
      Illustrated primarily by Claud Lovat Fraser, for Fisk
  - OTHER MATERIALS
    - Typescript list of Fisk's rare book collection, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 109-114)
      This collection was bought by the Yale University Library in 1956
    - Lists of Christmas cards sent by Fisk, 1923-49, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 115)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, (1 portfolio)
  Restricted Fragile Papers contains fragile originals, which may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies have been substituted in the main files for the originals.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Port 116-117: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 3, folder 97 (Box PORT, Folder 116-117)